Guide to the Highlands Women's Dialogue Records, 1992-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Highlands Women's Dialogue records 1992-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Highlands Institute for American Religious and Philosophical Thought. The Women's Dialogue.
1.2 Linear Feet 500 Items
The Highlands Institute for American Religious and Philosophical Thought (HIARPT) was established in Highlands, North Carolina, as a result of the expansion of the American Journal of Theology and Philosophy. The Women's Dialogue began in 1992 as a means to discuss theology and philosophy from a feminist perspective. It hosts annual seminars and monthly discussion groups on feminist theology.
Collection (2010-0173) (500 items; 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1992-2010) includes seminar files and materials from Women's Dialogue seminars, historical perspectives gathered by the Women's Dialogue members for their 10th anniversary, correspondence between members, information on speakers, finances, and membership rosters. Patricia Boyd's files, a separate series, contains additional seminar materials and other supplemental files on speakers and programs. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Highlands Women's Dialogue Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010.
Historical Note
The Highlands Institute for American Religious and Philosophical Thought (HIARPT) was established in Highlands, North Carolina, as a result of the expansion of the American Journal of Theology and Philosophy. Its original mission was to sponsor two conference series: one on Philosophical Theology (which began in 1988) and one on American Religious and Philosophical Thought (which began in 1990). These conferences run on a five-year schedule in Highlands.
The organization also developed an annual seminar series, beginning in 1990, that gradually expanded in scope and attendance. One result was the establishment of the Women's Dialogue, which began in 1992 as a means to discuss theology and philosophy from a feminist perspective. Writing Our Lives, the first Women's Dialogue Seminar was held in June 1993. Today, the Women's Dialogue hosts annual seminars and monthly discussion groups on feminist theology.
Collection Overview
The collection is separated into two series: the Women's Dialogue series and the Patricia Boyd Papers series. Despite this division, both series include corresponding files and materials from the activities of the Women's Dialogue.
The majority of the collection consists of program information and planning from the Dialogue's annual seminars. The earliest material dates from the 1996 seminar, but the seminars from the year 2001 and later all have more information and details. Common materials include the seminar's agenda, some information about its speaker, and other registration or logistical information. Other aspects of the collection include some historical financial records, mailing lists and rosters, and program files or speaker information.
One file is full of autobiographies of some of the Women's Dialogue founders, written in 1993. Another interesting component is the survey conducted by the Women's Dialogue during its tenth anniversary in 2001-2002, which resulted in the publishing of the History of the Women's Dialogue. For more information on the Women's Dialogue and its parent organization, the Highlands Institute for American Religious and Philosophical Thought, visit their website: http://www.hiarpt.org/index.html.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Highlands Institute for American Religious and Philosophical Thoguht. The Women's Dialogue
Boyd, Patricia
Feminist theology -- Seminars
Highlands (N.C.)
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Women's Dialogue, 1993-2010, (2 boxes)
  - History of the Women's Dialogue surveys and essays, 2001-2002 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical essays by Women's Dialogue founders, 1993
  - Seminar materials, 1993-2009
  - Seminars, 1996-2000
  - Seminar, "Feminist Pragmatism," 2001
  - Seminar, "Women and Faith Communities in the 21st Century," 2002
  - Seminar, "A Longing Look at Chimpanzees: Learning About Women Through the Eyes of an Other," 2003
  - Seminar, Marjorie Suchocki film festival, 2004
  - Seminar, "How are pacifism and feminism related? Virginia Woolf's 3 Guineas," 2005
  - Seminar, "The Goddess Phenomenon," 2006
  - Seminar, "Distinguishing healthy, unhealthy, and toxic religious systems," 2007
  - Seminar, "Conversations on religion, feminism, ethics, and spirituality: How/Can the well-being of women matter more?," 2008
  - Seminar, "Feminism and Us in the 21st Century," 2009
  - Finances, 2006-2009
  - Speakers, 1995-2007
  - Mailing list, 2001-2009 and undated (Box 2)
- Patricia Boyd Papers, 1992-2010, (1 box)
  - Master rosters (Box 2)
  - Programs, 2001-2003 (2 folders)
  - Seminars, 1999-2005
  - Seminars, 2007-2010 (7 folders)
  - Finances, 2007-2008
  - Feedback, 2008
  - Speaker suggestions
  - Old draft of organizing group, 1992-1993
  - Labels